<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wali-reheman.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://wali-reheman.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-15T03:06:28+00:00</updated><id>https://wali-reheman.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wali Reheman</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Course Hub for Conduct of Inquiry I Lab - SPA 096</title><link href="https://wali-reheman.com/blog/2024/Teaching_Conduct_I_Lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Course Hub for Conduct of Inquiry I Lab - SPA 096"/><published>2024-05-05T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-05T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wali-reheman.com/blog/2024/Teaching_Conduct_I_Lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wali-reheman.com/blog/2024/Teaching_Conduct_I_Lab/"><![CDATA[ <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css2?family=Lato&amp;display=swap"/> <style>body{font-family:'Lato',sans-serif;line-height:1.6;color:#333}h2,h3{margin-top:1.5rem;border-bottom:1px solid #eaeaea;padding-bottom:.5rem}.post-content{margin:none;padding:1rem 0}.resource-section{background:#f7f7f7;padding:20px;border-radius:none;margin-bottom:1.5rem}.download-btn{display:inline-block;padding:8px 16px;background-color:#0056b3;color:#fff;text-decoration:none;border-radius:4px;transition:background-color .3s ease;margin-top:.5rem}.download-btn:hover{background-color:#003f7f}</style> <div class="post-content"> <p>This course is a lab supplement to the <strong>SPA 612: Conduct of Inquiry I</strong>. This lab is an introduction to R and Stata programming, focusing on data wrangling, visualization, basic regression and result output. The course aims to equip students with essential skills to manipulate, analyze, and visualize data using R and Stata.</p> <h2>Syllabus</h2> <div class="resource-section"> <p>The syllabus outlines the course objectives, grading, and schedule for the Conduct of Inquiry I Lab.</p> <a href="/assets/pdf/conduct_1_lab/SPA_096_Conduct_of_inquiry_Lab.pdf" class="download-btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Download Syllabus </a> </div> <h2>Session 1: Basic R Operations</h2> <div class="resource-section"> <p>Session 1 covers the basic R operations to introduce students to basic data manipulation, arithmetic, and vectorized operations in R.</p> <a href="/assets/pdf/conduct_1_lab/Session 1 Handout.pdf" class="download-btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Download Handout </a> </div> <h2>Session 2: Introduction to dplyr</h2> <div class="resource-section"> <p>Session 2 covers dplyr package for data manipulation in R. You will learn how to use its key functions such as <code>select()</code>, <code>filter()</code>, <code>arrange()</code>, and <code>mutate()</code>. We will also cover advanced topics like using <code>across()</code> for applying functions to multiple columns.</p> <a href="/assets/pdf/conduct_1_lab/Session 2 Handout.pdf" class="download-btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Download Handout </a> </div> <h2>Session 3: Basic Stata Operations and Data Manipulation</h2> <div class="resource-section"> <p>Session 3 covers into the basic Stata operations, and provides an introduction to the Data Manipulation equivalent of <code>dplyr</code> in Stata.</p> <a href="/assets/pdf/conduct_1_lab/Session 3 Handout.pdf" class="download-btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Download Handout </a> </div> <h2>Session 4: R Practice A </h2> <div class="resource-section"> <p>Session 4 is a in-class pratice session for R, we will use R packages we learned so far to complete a in-class practice.</p> <a href="/assets/pdf/conduct_1_lab/Session 4 Handout.pdf" class="download-btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Download Handout </a> </div> <h2>Session 5: Aggregating and reshaping DataA </h2> <div class="resource-section"> <p>The <code>summarize()</code> function from the dplyr package is a powerful tool for creating summary statistics of your data. It allows you to collapse a dataset to a single row or a summary for each group of observations. In this tutorial, we’ll explore the basic and advanced uses of <code>summarize()</code>, as well as ways to reshape data.</p> <a href="/assets/pdf/conduct_1_lab/Session 5 Handout.pdf" class="download-btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Download Handout </a> </div> </div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/B-roll/icons_Data%20Analytics-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/B-roll/icons_Data%20Analytics-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/B-roll/icons_Data%20Analytics-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/B-roll/icons_Data%20Analytics.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="Rstats"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First-Year PhD Students! No Need to Master Statistics Overnight</title><link href="https://wali-reheman.com/blog/2024/First-Year-PhD-Students-No-Need-to-Master-Statistics-Overnight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First-Year PhD Students! No Need to Master Statistics Overnight"/><published>2024-05-04T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wali-reheman.com/blog/2024/First-Year-PhD-Students-No-Need-to-Master-Statistics-Overnight</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wali-reheman.com/blog/2024/First-Year-PhD-Students-No-Need-to-Master-Statistics-Overnight/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction-to-practical-statistical-learning">Introduction to Practical Statistical Learning</h2> <p>Embarking on your journey as a first-year PhD student can be overwhelming, especially when you’re faced with the seemingly daunting realm of statistics. But here’s a reassuring truth: you don’t need to be an advanced statistician to excel in research. Instead of focusing on highly technical methods right from the start, you can develop a strong foundation by taking a practical approach to statistical learning.</p> <p>As students, we sometimes fall into the trap of believing that mastering complex statistical concepts is the only way to conduct rigorous research. In reality, understanding the essentials and applying them effectively is far more valuable. The goal should be to develop a clear comprehension of statistical inference, explore data thoughtfully, and apply appropriate models for your research questions.</p> <p>This blog will guide you through practical strategies for approaching statistical inference, including resources, tools, and best practices that can build your confidence. We will explore the significance of understanding your data, introduce foundational resources like “Regression and Other Stories,” and discuss practical ways to implement statistical models, even if you’re not an expert in advanced techniques. By adopting this mindset, you’ll be better equipped to handle real-world data challenges and contribute valuable insights to the field.</p> <p>Ultimately, remember that learning statistics is a gradual process, and it’s important to build skills over time. With persistence, curiosity, and a practical approach, you’ll find yourself making meaningful progress in statistical learning.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="basic-knowledge">Basic Knowledge</h2> <p>If I have to pick one book to recommend to social science students for a foundational understanding of statistics, it would be:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://avehtari.github.io/ROS-Examples/index.html">Regression and Other Stories</a></li> </ul> <p>This book provides a practical introduction to statistical modeling and data analysis from a Bayesian perspective, which complements frequentist methods by emphasizing predictions and Bayesian model averaging. Co-authored by Andrew Gelman, Jennifer Hill, and Aki Vehtari, the text builds on simple foundations to develop an intuitive understanding of regression models. It’s particularly useful for those who want a deep dive into the philosophy and application of statistics in the social sciences. The accompanying examples and code in R make it accessible and practically oriented, ensuring that readers not only understand statistical concepts but also know how to implement them in real-world scenarios.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="look-at-your-data">Look at Your Data</h2> <h3 id="statistical-inference-based-on-observational-data">Statistical Inference Based on Observational Data</h3> <p>As a student, we are at a really early stage of our career, it might be hard for us to get first-hand data. Starting from existing datasets might be helpful, there are always good research published using existing observational datasets. Dr. Yiqing XU has a very useful checklist for conducting research using observational data:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://yiqingxu.org/public/checklist.pdf">A Basic Checklist for Observational Studies in Political Science</a></li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="additional-tips-for-first-year-phd-students">Additional Tips for First-Year PhD Students</h2> <p>Below are some suggestions to help you get comfortable with statistical learning and research during your first year:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Start With Familiar Tools</strong></p> <ul> <li>Pick one statistical software (R, Python, Stata, etc.) and stick to it until you’re comfortable with the basics.</li> <li>Focus on common tasks: data cleaning, descriptive statistics, simple plots, and standard regression models.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Embrace Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA)</strong></p> <ul> <li>Always begin by exploring your dataset: check for missing values, outliers, and distributions of key variables.</li> <li>Create simple visualizations (histograms, scatter plots) to get an intuitive feel for the data before diving into complex models.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Set Realistic Goals</strong></p> <ul> <li>Avoid the pressure to use cutting-edge techniques right away. Work step by step, mastering one concept at a time.</li> <li>Schedule weekly goals, such as learning a specific R function or replicating a simple analysis from a journal article.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Focus on Interpretation, Not Just Computation</strong></p> <ul> <li>When you run a regression, make sure you understand the meaning of coefficients, standard errors, and p-values.</li> <li>Practice explaining your findings in plain language. This helps you see if you actually understand what the model is telling you.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Collaborate and Ask Questions</strong></p> <ul> <li>Share your analysis process with peers—collaboration often leads to insights you might not catch alone.</li> <li>Don’t be shy about asking for help. Online forums (like StackOverflow for coding questions) are great resources if you feel stuck.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Document Your Steps</strong></p> <ul> <li>Keep a detailed log of your code, decisions, and reasoning. It helps when you revisit a project months later.</li> <li>Version control tools like Git (with GitHub) can save you headaches and help you track changes over time.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Learn from Existing Projects</strong></p> <ul> <li>Explore data repositories (e.g., ICPSR, World Bank Open Data) to find datasets related to your field.</li> <li>Attempt to replicate results from published studies. Replication hones your analytical skills and deepens your understanding of methods.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Stay Organized</strong></p> <ul> <li>Design a clear folder structure for your research projects, separating raw data, cleaned data, code, and outputs.</li> <li>This will help you keep track of each step in your analysis and make it easier to share your work with advisors or collaborators.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Engage with Your Research Community</strong></p> <ul> <li>Attend seminars, workshops, or brown-bag discussions in your department.</li> <li>These sessions often reveal new methods, provide feedback on ongoing research, and offer networking opportunities.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Develop a Growth Mindset</strong></p> </li> </ol> <ul> <li>Expect to make mistakes—that’s part of the learning curve.</li> <li>Each time you get stuck, view it as a chance to deepen your understanding.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Starting a PhD in the social sciences doesn’t mean you need to become an expert statistician overnight. By focusing on practical strategies, building a solid foundation with resources like <em>Regression and Other Stories</em>, and leveraging existing datasets, you’ll gain the confidence to handle real-world data challenges. The key is to stay curious, be patient with yourself, and approach learning statistics as an ongoing process.</p> <p>Remember: <strong>it’s not about memorizing every formula</strong>—it’s about knowing how to think about data, ask the right questions, and apply the methods that best serve your research. Keep exploring, keep testing your ideas, and you’ll gradually develop the intuition and skill set you need to excel.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="advise"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Practical Statistical Learning]]></summary></entry></feed>